<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="flow3.chapter.aopframework"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>AOP Framework</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Aspect-Oriented Programming (AOP) is a programming paradigm which
    complements Object-Oriented Programming (OOP) by separating
    <firstterm>concerns</firstterm> of a software application to improve
    modularization. The separation of concerns (SoC) aims for making a
    software easier to maintain by grouping features and behavior into
    manageable parts which all have a specific purpose and business to take
    care of.</para>

    <para>OOP already allows for modularizing concerns into distinct methods,
    classes and packages. However, some concerns are difficult to place as
    they cross the boundaries of classes and even packages. One example for
    such a <firstterm>cross-cutting concern</firstterm> is security: Although
    the main purpose of a <package>Forum</package> package is to display and
    manage posts of a forum, it has to implement some kind of security to
    assert that only moderators can approve or delete posts. And many more
    packages need a similar functionality for protect the creation, deletion
    and update of records. AOP enables you to move the security (or any other)
    aspect into its own package and leave the other objects with clear
    responsibilities, probably not implementing any security
    themselves.</para>

    <para>Aspect-Oriented Programming has been around in other programming
    languages for quite some time now and sophisticated solutions taking
    advantage of AOP exist. FLOW3's AOP framework allows you to use of the
    most popular AOP techniques in your own PHP application. In contrast to
    other approaches it doesn't require any special PHP extensions, additional
    compile steps or modification of the target code – and it's a breeze to
    configure.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>In case you are unsure about some terms used in this introduction
      or later in this chapter, it's a good idea looking them up (for example
      at <link xl:href="http://en.wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</link>). Don't
      think that you're the only one who has never heard of a
      <firstterm>Pointcut</firstterm> or <firstterm>SoC</firstterm><footnote>
          <para>SoC could, by the way, also mean <quote>Self-organized
          criticality</quote> or <quote>Service-oriented Computing</quote> or
          refer to Google's <quote>Summer of Code</quote> ...</para>
        </footnote> – we had a hard time learning these too. However, it's
      worth the hassle, as a common vocabulary improves the communication
      between developers a lot.</para>
    </tip>

    <section>
      <title>AOP concepts and terminology</title>

      <para>Let's stay with the example of a <package>Forum</package> for a
      while. The classes of the forum don't implement security themselves, but
      somehow we have to make sure that whenever a method
      <methodname>deletePost()</methodname> is called, a security check takes
      place. The class containing the delete method is called the
      <firstterm>target class</firstterm>. We have a new
      <firstterm>aspect</firstterm> called "security" which we'd like to
      <firstterm>weave</firstterm> into that class. Whenever the method
      <methodname>deletePost()</methodname> is called, a <firstterm>method
      interceptor</firstterm> defined by an <firstterm>around
      advice</firstterm> will intercept the <firstterm>target
      method</firstterm> and only proceed if the operation is allowed in the
      current security context.</para>

      <para>At the first (and the second, third, ...) glance, the terms used
      in the AOP context are not really intuitive. But, similar to most of the
      other AOP frameworks, we better stick to them, to keep a common language
      between developers. Here they are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Aspect</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An aspect is the part of the application which cross-cuts
            the core concerns of multiple objects. In FLOW3, aspects are
            implemented as regular classes which are tagged by the
            <markup>@aspect</markup> annotation. The methods of an aspect
            class represent advices, the properties act as an anchor for
            introductions.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Join point</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A join point is a point in the flow of a program. Examples
            are the execution of a method or the throw of an exception. In
            FLOW3, join points are represented by the
            <classname>\F3\FLOW3\AOPJoinPoint</classname> object which
            contains more information about the circumstances like name of the
            called method, the passed arguments or type of the exception
            thrown. A join point is an event which occurs during the program
            flow, not a definition which defines that point.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Advice</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An advice is the action taken by an aspect at a particular
            join point. Advices are implemented as methods of the aspect
            class. These methods are executed before and / or after the join
            point is reached.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Pointcut</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The pointcut defines a set of joinpoints which need to be
            matched before running an advice. The pointcut is configured by a
            <firstterm>pointcut expression</firstterm> which defines when and
            where an advice should be executed. FLOW3 uses methods in an
            aspect class as anchors for pointcut declarations.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Pointcut expression</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A poincut expression is the condition under which a
            joinpoint should match. It may, for example, define that
            joinpoints only match on the execution of a (target-) method with
            a certain name. Pointcut expressions are used in pointcut- and
            advice declarations.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Target</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A class or method being adviced by one or more aspects is
            referred to as a target class /-method.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Introduction</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An introduction redeclares the target class to implement an
            additional interface. By declaring an introduction it is possible
            to introduce new interfaces and an implementation of the required
            methods without touching the code of the original class.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The following terms are related to advices:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Before advice</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A before advice is executed before the target method is
            being called, but cannot prevent the target method from being
            executed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>After returning advice</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An after returning advice is executed after returning from
            the target method. The result of the target method invocation is
            available to the after returning advice, but it can't change it.
            If the target method throws an exception, the after returning
            advice is not executed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>After throwing advice</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An after throwing advice is only executed if the target
            method throwed an exception. The after throwing advice may fetch
            the exception type from the join point object.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>After advice</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An after advice is executed after the target method has been
            called, no matter if an exception was thrown or not.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Around advice</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An around advice is wrapped around the execution of the
            target method. It may execute code before and after the invocation
            of the target method and may ultimately prevent the original
            method from being executed at all. An around advice is also
            responsible for calling other around advices at the same join
            point and returning either the original or a modified result for
            the target method.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Advice chain</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If more than one around advice exists for a join point, they
            are called in an onion-like advice chain: The first around advice
            probably executes some before-code, then calls the second around
            advice which calls the target method. The target method returns a
            result which can be modified by the second around advice, is
            returned to the first around advice which finally returns the
            result to the initiator of the method call. Any around advice may
            decide to proceed or break the chain and modify results if
            necessary.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>FLOW3 AOP concepts</title>

      <para>Aspect-Oriented Programming was, of course, not invented by
      us<footnote>
          <para>AOP was rather invented by <personname>
          <firstname>Gregor</firstname> <surname>Kiczales</surname>
          </personname>and his team at the <link
          xl:href="http://www.parc.com/">Xerox Palo Alto Research
          Center</link>. The original implementation was called <link
          xl:href="http://eclipse.org/aspectj">AspectJ</link> and is an
          extension to Java. It still serves as a de-facto standard and is now
          maintained by the Eclipse Foundation.</para>
        </footnote>. Since the initial release of the concept, dozens of
      implementations for various programming languages evolved. Although a
      few PHP-based AOP frameworks do exist, they followed concepts which did
      not match the goals of FLOW3 (to provide a powerful, yet
      developer-friendly solution) when the development of TYPO3 5.0 began. We
      therefore decided to create a sophisticated but pragmatic implementation
      which adopts the concepts of AOP but takes PHP's specialties and the
      requirements of typical FLOW3 applications into account. In a few cases
      this even lead to new features or simplifications because they were
      easier to implement in PHP compared to Java.</para>

      <para>FLOW3 pragmatically implements a reduced subset of AOP, which
      satisfies most needs of web applications. The join point model allows
      for intercepting method executions but provides no special support for
      advising field access<footnote>
          <para>Intercepting setting and retrieval of properties can easily be
          achieved by declaring a before-, after- or around advice.</para>
        </footnote>. For the sake of simplicity and performance, pointcuts
      don't allow criteria which have to be evaluated at runtime (such as
      matching argument values of a method) and pointcut expressions are based
      on well-known regular expressions instead of requiring the knowledge of
      a dedicated expression language. Pointcut filters and join point types
      are modularized and can be extended if more advanced requirements should
      arise in the future.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Implementation overview</title>

      <para>FLOW3's AOP framework does not require a pre-processor or an
      aspect-aware PHP interpreter to weave in advices. It is implemented and
      based on pure PHP and doesn't need any specific PHP extension. However,
      it does require the Object Manager to fulfill its task.</para>

      <para>FLOW3 uses PHP's reflection capabilities to analyze declarations
      of aspects, pointcuts and advices and implements method interceptors as
      a dynamic proxy. In accordance to the GoF patterns<footnote>
          <para>GoF means Gang of Four and refers to the authors of the
          classic book <citetitle>Design Patterns – Elements of Reusable
          Object-Oriented Software</citetitle></para>
        </footnote>, the proxy classes act as a placeholders for the target
      object. They are true subclasses of the original and override adviced
      methods by implementing a interceptor method. The proxy classes are
      generated automatically by the AOP framework and cached for further use.
      If a class has been adviced by some aspect, the Object Manager will only
      deliver instances of the proxy class instead of the original.</para>

      <para>The approach of storing generated proxy classes in files provides
      the whole advantage of dynamic weaving with a minimum performance hit.
      Debugging of proxied classes is still easy as they truly exist in real
      files.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Aspects</title>

    <para>Aspects are abstract containers which accommodate pointcut-,
    introduction- and advice declarations. In most frameworks, including
    FLOW3, aspects are defined as plain classes which are tagged (annotated)
    as an aspect. The following example shows the definition of a hypothetical
    <emphasis>FooSecurity</emphasis> aspect:</para>

    <example>
      <title>Declaration of an aspect</title>

      <programlisting language="php">namespace F3\MySecurityPackage;

/**
 * An aspect implementing security for Foo
 *
 * @package MySecurityPackage
 * @author  John Doe &lt;john@typo3.org&gt;
 * @aspect
 */
class FooSecurityAspect {

}</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>As you can see,
    <classname>\F3\MySecurityPackage\FooSecurityAspect</classname> is just a
    regular PHP class which may (actually must) contain methods and
    properties. What it makes it an aspect is solely the
    <markup>@aspect</markup> annotation mentioned in the class comment. The
    AOP framework recognizes this tag and registers the class as an
    aspect.</para>

    <note>
      <para>A void aspect class doesn't make any sense and if you try to run
      the above example, the AOP framework will throw an exception complaining
      that no advice, introduction or pointcut has been defined.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Pointcuts</title>

    <para>If we want to add security to foo, we need a method which carries
    out the security checks and a definition where and when this method should
    be executed. The method is an advice which we're going to declare in a
    later section, the <quote>where and when</quote> is defined by a pointcut
    expression in a pointcut declaration.</para>

    <para>You can either define the pointcut in the advice declaration or set
    up named pointcuts to help clarify their use.</para>

    <para>A named pointcut is represented by a method of an aspect class. It
    contains two pieces of information: The pointcut name, defined by the
    methodname, and the poincut expression, declared by an annotation. The
    following pointcut will match the execution of methods whose name starts
    with <quote>delete</quote>, mo matter in which class they are
    defined:</para>

    <example>
      <title>Declaration of a named pointcut</title>

      <programlisting language="php">   /**
	 * A pointcut which matches all methods whose name starts with "delete".
	 *
	 * <co xml:id="co.pointcutdeclaration.1"/>@pointcut method(.*-&gt;delete.*())
	 * @author John Doe &lt;john@typo3.org&gt;
	 */
	public function <co xml:id="co.pointcutdeclaration.2"/>deleteMethods() {}</programlisting>

      <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="co.pointcutdeclaration.1">
          <para>Declaration of the pointcut expression</para>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="co.pointcutdeclaration.2">
          <para>Name of the pointcut</para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>
    </example>

    <section>
      <title>Pointcut expressions</title>

      <para>As already mentioned, the pointcut expression configures the
      filters which are used to match against join points. It is comparable to
      an <function>if</function> condition in PHP: Only if the whole condition
      evaluates to <constant>TRUE</constant>, the statement is executed -
      otherwise it will be just ignored. If a pointcut expression evaluates to
      <constant>TRUE</constant>, the pointcut matches and advices which refer
      to this poincut become active.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The AOP framework <productname>AspectJ</productname> provides a
        complete pointcut language with dozens of pointcut types and
        expression constructs. FLOW3 makes do with only a small subset of that
        language, which we think already suffice for even complex enterprise
        applications. If you're interested in the original feature set, it
        doesn't hurt throwing a glance at the <link
        xl:href="http://www.eclipse.org/aspectj/doc/released/progguide/index.html">AspectJ
        Programming Guide</link>.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Pointcut designators</title>

      <para>A pointcut expression always consists of two parts: The poincut
      designator and its parameter(s). The following designators are supported
      by FLOW3:</para>

      <section>
        <title>method()</title>

        <para>The <function>method()</function> designator matches on the
        execution of methods with a certain name. The parameter specifies the
        class and method name, regular expressions can be used for more
        flexibility<footnote>
            <para>Internally, PHP's <function>preg_match()</function> function
            is used to match the method name. The regular expression will be
            enclosed by <literal>/^<replaceable>...</replaceable>$/</literal>
            (without the dots of course). Backslashes will be escaped to make
            namespace use possible without further hassle.</para>
          </footnote>. It follows the following scheme:</para>

        <synopsis>method(public|protected ClassName-&gt;methodName())</synopsis>

        <para>Specifying the visibility modifier (public or protected) is
        optional - if none is specified, both visibilities will match. The
        class- and method name can be specified as a regular expression. Here
        are some examples for matching method executions:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>method() pointcut designator</title>

            <para>Matches all public methods in class
            <classname>\F3\MyPackage\MyObject</classname>:</para>

            <para><code>method(public
            F3\MyPackage\MyObject-&gt;.*())</code></para>

            <para>Matches all delete methods (even protected and private ones)
            in any class of the package <package>MyPackage</package>:</para>

            <para><code>method(F3\MyPackage\.*-&gt;delete.*())</code></para>
          </example><note>
            <para>In other AOP frameworks, including
            <trademark>AspectJ</trademark> and <trademark>Spring</trademark>,
            the <function>method</function> designator does not exist. They
            rather use a more fine grained approach with designators such as
            <function>execution</function>, <function>call</function> and
            <function>cflow</function>. As FLOW3 only supports matching to
            method execution join points anyway, we decided to simplify things
            by allowing only a more general <function>method</function>
            designator.</para>
          </note></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>class()</title>

        <para>The <function>class()</function> designator matches on the
        execution of methods defined in a class with a certain name. The
        parameter specifies the class name, again regular expressions are
        allowed here. The <function>class()</function> designator follows this
        simple scheme:</para>

        <synopsis><function>class(<replaceable>classname</replaceable>)</function></synopsis>

        <para>An example for the usage of this designator:</para>

        <example>
          <title>class() pointcut designator</title>

          <para>Matches all methods in class
          <classname>F3\MyPackage\MyObject</classname>:</para>

          <para><code>class(F3\MyPackage\MyObject)</code></para>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>within()</title>

        <para>The <function>within()</function> designator matches on the
        execution of methods defined in a class of a certain type. A type
        matches if the class is a subclass of or implements an interface of
        the given name. The <function>within()</function> designator has this
        simple syntax:</para>

        <synopsis><function>within(<replaceable>type</replaceable>)</function></synopsis>

        <para>An example for the usage of
        <function>within()</function>:</para>

        <example>
          <title>within() pointcut designator</title>

          <para>Matches all methods in classes which implement the logger
          interface:</para>

          <para><code>within(\F3\FLOW3\Log\LoggerInterface)</code></para>

          <para>Matches all methods in classes which are part of the Foo
          layer:</para>

          <para><code>within(\F3\FLOW3\FooLayerInterface)</code></para>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>classTaggedWith()</title>

        <para>The <function>classTaggedWith()</function> designator matches on
        classes which are tagged with a certain annotation. As with class and
        method names, a regular expression can be used to describe the
        matching tags. The syntax of this designator is as follows:</para>

        <synopsis><function>classTaggedWith(<replaceable>tag</replaceable>)</function></synopsis>

        <example>
          <title>classTaggedWith() pointcut designator</title>

          <para>Matches all classes which are tagged with an "@entity"
          annotation:</para>

          <para><code>classTaggedWith(entity)</code></para>

          <para>Matches all classes which are tagged with an annotation
          starting with "@cool":</para>

          <para><code>classTaggedWith(cool.*)</code></para>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>methodTaggedWith()</title>

        <para>The <function>methodTaggedWith()</function> designator matches
        on methods which are tagged with a certain annotation. As with other
        pointcut designators, a regular expression can be used to describe the
        matching tags. The syntax of this designator is as follows:</para>

        <synopsis><function>methodTaggedWith(<replaceable>tag</replaceable>)</function></synopsis>

        <example>
          <title>methodTaggedWith() pointcut designator</title>

          <para>Matches all method which are tagged with an "@special"
          annotation:</para>

          <para><code>methodTaggedWith(special)</code></para>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>setting()</title>

        <para>The <code>setting()</code> designator matches if the given
        configuration option is set to TRUE, or if an optional given
        comparison value equals to its configured value. You can use this
        designator as follows:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>setting() pointcut designator</title>

            <para>Matches if <code>"my.configuration.option"</code> is set to
            TRUE in the current execution context:</para>

            <para><code>setting(my.configuration.option)</code></para>

            <para>Matches if <code>"my.configuration.option"</code> is equal
            to "AOP is cool" in the current execution context: (Note: single
            and double quotes are allowed)</para>

            <para><code>setting(my.configuration.option = 'AOP is
            cool')</code></para>
          </example></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>filter()</title>

        <para>If the built-in filters don't suit your needs you can even
        define your own custom filters. All you need to do is create a class
        implementing the
        <interfacename>\F3\FLOW3\AOP\Pointcut\PointcutFilterInterface</interfacename>
        and develop your own logic for the <methodname>matches()</methodname>
        method. The custom filter can then be invoked by using the
        <methodname>filter()</methodname> designator:</para>

        <synopsis><function>filter(<replaceable>CustomFilterObjectName</replaceable>)</function></synopsis>

        <example>
          <title>filter() pointcut designator</title>

          <para>If the current method matches is determined by the custom
          filter:</para>

          <para><code>filter(F3\MyPackage\MyCustomPointcutFilter)</code></para>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Combining pointcut expressions</title>

      <para>All pointcut expressions mentioned in previous sections can be
      combined into a whole expression, just like you may combine parts to an
      overall condition in an <function>if</function> construct. The supported
      operators are <quote>&amp;&amp;</quote>, <quote>||</quote> and
      <quote>!</quote> and they have the same meaning as in PHP. Nesting
      expressions with parentheses is not supported but you may refer to other
      pointcuts by specifying their full name (i.e. class- and method name).
      This final example shows how to combine and reuse pointcuts and
      ultimately build a hierarchy of pointcuts which can be used conveniently
      in advice declarations:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Combining pointcut expressions</title>

        <para><programlisting language="php">namespace F3\TestPackage;

/**
 * Fixture class for testing poincut definitions
 *
 * @package TestPackage
 * @aspect
 */
class PointcutTestingAspect {

	/**
	 * Pointcut which includes all method executions in
	 * pointcutTestingTargetClasses except those from Target
	 * Class number 3.
	 *
	 * @pointcut method(F3\TestPackage\PointcutTestingTargetClass.*-&gt;.*()) &amp;&amp; ⏎
      !method(F3\TestPackage\PointcutTestingTargetClass3-&gt;.*())
	 */
	public function pointcutTestingTargetClasses() {}

	/**
	 * Pointcut which consists of only the
	 * F3\TestPackage\OtherPointcutTestingTargetClass.
	 *
	 * @pointcut method(F3\TestPackage\OtherPointcutTestingTargetClass-&gt;.*())
	 */
	public function otherPointcutTestingTargetClass() {}

	/**
	 * A combination of both above pointcuts
	 *
	 * @pointcut F3\TestPackage\PointcutTestingAspect-&gt;pointcutTestingTargetClasses ⏎
      || F3\TestPackage\PointcutTestingAspect-&gt;otherPointcutTestingTargetClass
	 * @author Robert Lemke &lt;robert@typo3.org&gt;
	 */
	public function bothPointcuts() {}

	/**
	 * A pointcut which matches all classes from the service layer
	 *
	 * @pointcut within(\F3\FLOW3\ServiceLayerInterface)
	 */
	public function serviceLayerClasses() {}

	/**
	 * A pointcut which matches any method from the BasicClass and all classes
	 * from the service layer
	 *
	 * @pointcut method(F3\TestPackage\Basic.*-&gt;.*()) || within(F3\FLOW3\Service.*)
	 */
	public function basicClassOrServiceLayerClasses() {}
}</programlisting></para>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Declaring advice</title>

    <para>With the aspect and pointcuts in place we are now ready to declare
    the advice. Remember that an advice is the actual action, the
    implementation of the concern you want to weave in to some target. Advices
    are implemented as <emphasis>interceptors</emphasis> which may run before
    and / or after the target method is called. Four advice types allow for
    these different kinds of interception: Before, After returning, After
    throwing and Around.</para>

    <para>Other than being of a certain type, advices always come with a
    pointcut expression which defines the set of join points the advice
    applies for. The pointcut expression may, as we have seen earlier, refer
    to other named pointcuts.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Before advice</title>

      <para>A <emphasis>before advice</emphasis> allows for executing code
      before the target method is invoked. However, the advice cannot prevent
      the target method from being executed, nor can it take influence on
      other before advices at the same join point.</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Declaration of a before advice</title>

          <para><programlisting language="php">	/**
	 * Before advice which is invoked before any method call within the News 
	 * package
	 *
	 * @before class(F3\News\.*-&gt;.*())
	 */
	public function myBeforeAdvice(\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface ⏎
    $joinPoint) {
	}</programlisting></para>
        </example></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>After returning advice</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>after returning advice</emphasis> becomes active
      after the target method normally returns from execution (i.e. it doesn't
      throw an exception). After returning advices may read the result of the
      target method, but can't modify it.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Declaration of an after returning advice</title>

        <para><programlisting language="php">	/**
	 * After returning advice
	 *
	 * @afterreturning method(public F3\News\FeedAgregator-&gt;[import|update].*()) ⏎
      || F3\MyPackage\MyAspect-&gt;someOtherPointcut
	 */
	public function myAfterReturningAdvice(\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface ⏎
    $joinPoint) {
	}</programlisting></para>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>After throwing advice</title>

      <para>Similar to the <quote>after returning</quote> advice, the
      <emphasis>after throwing advice</emphasis> is invoked after method
      execution, but only if an exception was thrown.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Declaration of an after throwing advice</title>

        <para><programlisting language="php">	/**
	 * After throwing advice
	 *
	 * @afterthrowing within(F3\News\ImportantLayer)
	 */
	public function myAfterThrowingAdvice(\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface ⏎
    $joinPoint) {
	}</programlisting></para>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>After advice</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>after advice</emphasis> is a combination of
      <quote>after returning</quote> and <quote>after throwing</quote>: These
      advices become active after method execution, no matter if an exception
      was thrown or not.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Declaration of an after advice</title>

        <para><programlisting language="php">	/**
	 * After advice
	 *
	 * @after F3\MyPackage\MyAspect-&gt;justAPointcut
	 */
	public function myAfterAdvice(\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface $joinPoint) {
	}</programlisting></para>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Around advice</title>

      <para>Finally, the <emphasis>around advice</emphasis> takes total
      control over the target method and intercepts it completely. It may
      decide to call the original method or not and even modify the result of
      the target method or return a completely different one. Obviously the
      around advice is the most powerful and should only be used if the
      concern can't be implemented with the alternative advice types. You
      might already guess how an around advice is declared:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Declaration of an around advice</title>

        <para><programlisting language="php">   /**
	 * Around advice
	 *
	 * @around F3\MyPackage\MyAspect-&gt;justAPointcut
	 */
	public function myAroundAdvice(\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface $joinPoint) {
	}</programlisting></para>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Implementing advice</title>

    <para>The final step after declaring aspects, pointcuts and advices is to
    fill the advices with life. The implementation of an advice is located in
    the same method it has been declared. In that regard, an aspect class
    behaves like any other object in FLOW3 – you therefore can take advantage
    of dependency injection in case you need other objects to fulfill the task
    of your advice.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Accessing join points</title>

      <para>As you have seen in the previous section, advice methods always
      expect an argument of the type
      <interfacename>\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface</interfacename>. This
      join point object contains all important information about the current
      join point. Methods like <methodname>getClassName()</methodname> or
      <methodname>getMethodArguments()</methodname> let the advice method
      classify the current context and enable you to implement advices in a
      way that they can be reused in different situations. For a full
      description of the join point object refer to the API
      documentation.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Advice chains</title>

      <para>Around advices are a special advice type in that they have the
      power to completely intercept the target method. For any other advice
      type, the advice methods are called by the proxy class one after
      another. In case of the around advice, the methods form a chain where
      each link is responsible to pass over control to the next.</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Control flow of an advice chain</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                         fileref="AOPFramework_AdviceChain.png" scalefit="1"
                         width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>

      <para>Let's put our knowledge into practice and start with a simple
      example. First we would like to log each access to methods within
      certain package. The following code will just do that:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Simple logging with aspects</title>

        <programlisting language="php">namespace F3\MyPackage;

/**
 * A logging aspect
 *
 * @package MyPackage
 * @aspect
 */
class LoggingAspect {

	/**
	 * @var \F3\FLOW3\Log\LoggerInterface A logger implementation
	protected $logger;

	/**
	 * For logging we need a logger, which we will get injected automatically by 
	 * the Object Manager
	 *
	 * @param  \F3\FLOW3\Log\SystemLoggerInterface $logger The System Logger
	 * @return void
	 */
	public function injectSystemLogger(\F3\FLOW3\Log\SystemLoggerInterface ⏎
    $systemLogger) {
		$this-&gt;logger = $systemLogger;
	}

	/**
	 * Before advice, logs all access to methods of our package
	 *
	 * @param  \F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface $joinPoint: The current join point
	 * @return void
	 * @before method(F3\MyPackage\.*-&gt;.*())
	 */
	public function logMethodExecution(\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface $joinPoint) {
		$logMessage = 'The method ' . $joinPoint-&gt;getMethodName() . ' in class ' . ⏎
    $joinPoint-&gt;getClassName() . ' has been called.';
		$this-&gt;logger-&gt;log($logMessage);
	}
}</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>Note that we are using dependency injection for getting the system
      logger instance to stay independent from any specific logging
      implementation. We don't have to care about the kind of logger and where
      it comes from.</para>

      <para>Finally an example for the implementation of an around advice: For
      a guest book, we want to reject the last name <quote>Sarkosh</quote>
      (because it should be <quote>Skårhøj</quote>), every time it is
      submitted. Admittedly you probably wouldn't implement this great feature
      as an aspect, but it's easy enough to demonstrate the idea. For
      illustration purposes, we don't define the pointcut expression in place
      but refer to a named pointcut.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Implementation of an around advice</title>

        <para><programlisting language="php">namespace F3\MyPackage;

/**
 * A lastname rejection aspect
 *
 * @package MyPackage
 * @aspect
 */
class LastNameRejectionAspect {

	/**
	 * A pointcut which matches all guestbook submission method invocations
	 *
	 * @pointcut method(\F3\Guestbook\SubmissionHandlingThingy-&gt;submit())
	 */
	public function guestbookSubmissionPointcut() {}

	/**
	 * Around advice, rejects the lastname "Sarkosh"
	 *
	 * @param  \F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface $joinPoint The current join point
	 * @return mixed Result of the target method
	 * @around F3\MyPackage\LastNameRejectionAspect-&gt;guestbookSubmissionPointcut
	 */
	public function rejectLastName(\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface $joinPoint) {
		if ($joinPoint-&gt;getMethodArgument('lastName') == 'Sarkosh') {
			throw new Exception('Sarkosh is not a valid lastname - should be Skårhøj!');
		}
		$result = $joinPoint-&gt;getAdviceChain()-&gt;proceed($joinPoint);
		return $result;
	}
}</programlisting></para>
      </example>

      <para>Please note that if the last name is correct, we proceed with the
      remaining links in the advice chain. This is very important to assure
      that the original (target-) method is finally called. And don't forget
      to return the result of the advice chain ...</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Introductions</title>

    <para>Introductions (also known as <firstterm>Inter-type
    Declarations</firstterm>) allow to subsequently implement an interface in
    a given target class. The (usually) newly introduced methods (required by
    the new interface) can then be implemented by declaring an advice. If no
    implementation is defined, an empty placeholder method will be generated
    automatically to satisfy the contract of the introduced interface.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Declaring introductions</title>

      <para>Like advices, introductions are declared by annotations. But in
      contrast to advices, the anchor for an introduction declaration is a
      property of the aspect class. The annotation tag follows this
      syntax:</para>

      <para><markup>@introduce <replaceable>NewInterfaceName</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>PointcutExpression</replaceable></markup></para>

      <para>Although the <replaceable>PoincutExpression</replaceable> is just
      a normal pointcut expression, which may also refer to named pointcuts,
      be aware that only expressions filtering for
      <emphasis>classes</emphasis> make sense. You cannot use the
      <function>method()</function> pointcut designator in this context and
      will typically take the <function>class()</function> designator
      instead.</para>

      <para>The following example introduces a new interface
      <interfacename>NewInterface</interfacename> to the class
      <classname>OldClass </classname>and also provides an implementation of
      the method <methodname>newMethod</methodname>.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Declaring introductions</title>

        <programlisting language="php">namespace F3\MyPackage;

/**
 * An aspect for demonstrating introductions
 *
 * @package MyPackage
 * @aspect
 */
class IntroductionAspect {

	/**
	 * Introduces \F3\MyPackage\NewInterface to the class \F3\MyPackage\OldClass:
	 *
	 * @introduce F3\MyPackage\NewInterface, class(F3\MyPackage\OldClass)
	 */
	public $newInterface;

	/**
	 * Around advice, implements the new method "newMethod" of the
	 * "NewInterface" interface
	 *
	 * @param  \F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface $joinPoint The current join point
	 * @return void
	 * @around method(F3\MyPackage\OldClass-&gt;newMethod())
	 */
	public function newMethod(\F3\FLOW3\AOP\JoinPointInterface $joinPoint) {
			// We call the advice chain, in case any other advice is declared for
			// this method, but we don't care about the result.
		$someResult = $joinPoint-&gt;getAdviceChain-&gt;proceed($joinPoint);

		$a = $joinPoint-&gt;getMethodArgument('a');
		$b = $joinPoint-&gt;getMethodArgument('b');
		return $a + $b;
	}
}</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Implementation details</title>

    <section>
      <title>AOP proxy mechanism</title>

      <para>The following diagram illustrates the building process of a proxy
      class:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Proxy building process</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                       fileref="AOPFramework_ProxyBuildingProcess.png"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
