<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:ns6="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <para>FLOW3 is based on the newest technologies of tomorrow like for example
  namespaces. These technologies aren't available in the stable PHP 5.2
  releases at the moment, but are implemented in PHP 5.3. It has no final
  release until now, so operating system distributors do not provide PHP 5.3
  packages. You can find instructions to install the newest release candidate
  of PHP 5.3 for widely used operating systems in the appendixes.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>The following minimum requirements are operating system independent.
    Developers told about working instances on Debian Linux, MacOS, Windows XP
    and Windows Vista.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>PHP 5.3 RC2 or newer (but not PHP 6)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PHP modules: mbstring, pdo, sqlite</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PHP configuration: magic_quotes_gpc = off</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Apache modules: mod_rewrite</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Apache configuration: AllowOverride FileInfo</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>(Other webservers (f.e. IIS) could work, but have not been tested
    until now)</para>

    <para>We have written <link linkend="appendix.install.php53">installation
    instructions for PHP 5.3</link> that might be helpful for you.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installion of FLOW3</title>

    <para>These steps require the server requirements to be set up.
    Instruction on how to do that can be found in the appendixes.</para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>Download the FLOW3 distribution from
        <uri>http://flow3.typo3.org/download/</uri></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Unzip / un-phar it to the document root of the webserver (often
        "htdocs")<note>
            <para>It is highly recommended to change the document root of the
            webserver to the <filename>Public</filename> subfolder of the
            FLOW3 distribution!</para>
          </note></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>The webserver needs write permissions for some subfolders. The
        FLOW3 distribution provides a helper script for Unix like operating
        systems, which sets the permissions. Change to the top level folder of
        the FLOW3 distribution, there you will find the script
        <filename>setfilepermissions.sh</filename>. Execute this script
        providing the webserver user and group as parameters. On Debian Linux
        (Lenny) the commando would look like this:</para>

        <para><command>./setfilepermissions.sh www-data
        www-data</command></para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <para>Now you can check if FLOW3 works by pointing your browser to
    <uri>http://<replaceable>&lt;hostname&gt;/</replaceable></uri> . If
    everything works you should see the Welcome screen of the FLOW3
    distribution (this may take some time on the first call, because FLOW3
    needs to initialize itself and to create caching data):<figure>
        <title>The FLOW3 welcome screen</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="WelcomeScreen.png"
                         scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure></para>

    <tip>
      <para>On Windows systems PHP causes problems with long filenames. To
      avoid errors you should change the configuration of the cache to a place
      that leads to a very short absolute filepath, for example
      <filename>C:\t\</filename> or <filename>C:\t\x\</filename> (if you want
      to install more than one instance of FLOW3). Do that by adding the
      following lines to the file
      <filename>Configuration/FLOW3.yaml</filename> in your FLOW3-Distribution
      (the indenting must be done with two spaces):<programlisting>utility:
  environment:
    temporaryDirectoryBase: C:/t/x/</programlisting></para>
    </tip>

    <tip>
      <para>If (on Windows) you see the XAMPP default page after calling the
      FLOW3 URI, you might have forgotten to add the port number.</para>
    </tip>

    <note>
      <para>The persistence framework / content repository stores its data in
      an already set up sqlite database by default. It can be changed to a
      real database like for example MySQL. This requires some configuration
      which will be covered here later.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setup Eclipse PDT for PHP 5.3</title>

    <para>PHP 5.3 introduced the support of namespaces. This is a completly
    new syntax in PHP which is not supported by most editors (yet). Even the
    stable version of Eclipse PDT doesn't support namespaces syntax. So you
    have to install some Release Candidate of PDT 2.1, if you don't want to
    see all those red syntax-error-symbols in your php-files.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
